hello I want to tell you about tape
script I will consider in typescript
next what's tape script tape inheritance
syntax and variable declaration
interface generics and classes one-step
script tip script is developed by the
company Microsoft his actual creator is
programmer unders Helzberg tape script
immediately started to develop as open
source project tip script is not another
programming language is just a superset
of JavaScript with optional static
taking its who written it's right and
one top JavaScript tape script code
compile it in JavaScript code next tip
script has next type numbers drink
boolean its simple types and array tuple
and nom know define it would never and
any please don't use type any because
this is bad practice syntax and variable
declaration variables are the quality in
the same way in JavaScript using
keywords lead and Const you can define
multiple valid types in the variables
for the variables this is example
variable X can have a type numbers in
boolean another type will case one error
next array arrays are declared in two
method
first method with name type and square
breakers
second is class name Arry and name type
in angel brackets - PO tuple is a list
that is presented in memory as an array
but we clearly described the types that
we have to include this example purple
also we can to make type assertion
assert so we have to we have to method
first method it with helpful enter
brackets second is with help keyword us
next we can to describe interfaces that
serve as templates for object in the
first case this is example in the first
case we will get the correct result in
the second case we will get error
because we didn't specify a well you
hide in the soul in such a situation we
must use the optional fields via
question mark how one slide fields we
are question marks mark and now we did
we don't have the mistake the properties
can be also read-only
we need to use keywords only but we need
to immaturely this property
this example fields which is read-only
interfaces can be inherited from each
order and then the inherit interface
needs to contain the fields of the
parent we need to use keyword extends
this is interface person
this is parent interface employer
extends person next dynamics generic is
a generic exact function functions that
is not attached it to tape the generic
is created using angel breaks after name
fun so specifies observe the name of our
type and use it for food by alia ste
[Music]
generics can be airing classes and
another next classes classes in Cape
script are to describe in style six Atma
scripts six first we spit Sofia the
field and then his type in class
constructor is the same this is example
classes are inherited by using the
keyword extends in tape script we can
use common object-oriented patterns one
of the one of the most fundamental
patterns patterns in was buzzard
programming is being able to extend
existing classes to
create new ones using inheritance let's
take a look at example this is example
this is example this example shows the
most basic inheritance feud future
classes inherit properties and method
from buyers base classes base class this
is animal and cosmetics tense animal and
now class snake have method move we
attached the base class using the
keyword super house this no idea what
super
tape script has access modifier public
pre-weighed protected and read-only
public fields are full at the Sybil to
the user they are available directly for
from the object reference provide
private fields are hidden from the user
access to them is only inside the class
this is public field with object
reference object animal field name
private field don't inheritance
protected field works the same how
private but it is inheritance
this is exam protected fields read-only
we can make properties read-only by
using the read-only keywords read only
properties so must being its illicit
at their declaration or in the
constructor we can also create static
members of a class those that are
visible on the class itself rather
rather than one instance instances and
finally how to start we can start
install we have package manager manager
npm npm install' gu about a script or
not global and at all we can use tape
script in compiling code with the
command TST and file name this is all
thank you good bye